[Music]
radiohead is no stranger to television
and film with their song showing up in a
variety of shows and movies you can most
likely name at least one memorable
occurrence but with a few exceptions
when a Radiohead song appears in a show
or a film you can guarantee that it is
therefore very significant reasons uses
of the Bands songs range from the very
obvious and prominent
[Music]
- barely even noticeable you know
kaamika but regardless of how it's used
Radiohead's music is rarely just a
stylistic flourish music basically is
like mathematics you know and you're
trying to form patterns patterns that
make you understand what is around you
and patterns that help you get through
the next day
[Music]
[Laughter]
when we hear a Radiohead song
accompanying a scene we are forced to
dig a little deeper take the opening
scene of incentives directed by Denis
Villeneuve the film takes place in the
Middle East but rather than traditional
Middle Eastern music we immediately get
a Radiohead song regarding this decision
Villeneuve stated the Radiohead song was
attached to the opening of the film from
day one one of the ideas behind the song
is for it to be clear that it will be a
Westerners point of view about this
world an imposters point of view that it
will be a fiction when you put the image
with an Arabic or Middle Eastern song it
looks authentic and I didn't like that
at all Radiohead is explicitly used as
an immediate tone Center for the film
the song creates a distance and forces
us into the perspective of an outsider
[Music]
to really feel the impact of the
Radiohead song let's replace it with
some middle-eastern inspired music
[Music]
we are no longer positioned where
Villeneuve has so thoughtfully placed us
we are enveloped in this world which in
this case creates for a more traditional
and less impactful viewing experience as
a band Radiohead is I guess what you
could refer to as cinematic in addition
to movie quality music videos two of
their key members are talented film
composers Thom Yorke kicked off his
scoring career with the Suspiria remake
and guitarist Jonny Greenwood has proven
himself to be one of the best in the
business
scoring films like there will be blood
the master phantom thread and you were
never really here but besides the
members having knowledge of cinematic
composing the band's unique sound
actually lends itself to cinema though
often classified as alternative rock
Radiohead's music transcends genres
listen to the opening scene of Vanilla
Sky
[Music]
open your eyes
this song is rather electronic sounding
and actually suits this introductory
scene better than any original
composition could director Cameron Crowe
who surely knows great soundtracks
stated that this particular song is like
you've ripped open the human mind and
it's the thoughts and sounds of what
goes on in the psyche that's what we
want at Vanilla Sky to feel like
everything in its right place is a
rather uncomfortable piece of music it's
mechanical and unwelcoming and not very
catchy at all
additionally the lyrics reflect the
appearance based fastidiousness of Tom
Cruise's character this song
single-handedly introduces us to the
tone of this world
[Music]
we've looked at two examples of opening
a film with a Radiohead song so now
let's look at a film that closes with
one Denis Villeneuve followed up in
Sandy's with prisoners like in Sandy's
opened with a Radiohead song prisoners
ends with one and it's barely even
noticeable in a movie that relies so
heavily on traditional non-diegetic
scoring the introduction of a song with
lyrics is a little alarming and
evocative we realize that this song is
actually diegetic and is coming from the
workers boom box one of the workers
abruptly turns it off not allowing the
melody to resolve this minor detail may
seem insignificant but how does
prisoners end it's ambiguous it feels
unfinished when we look at codex as an
actual song not what we hear in the film
the song itself never truly resolves
have a listen to the ending
[Music]
it feels like it should be continuing
but it doesn't much like prisoners when
we look at majority of the works that
use Radiohead music we have things like
Westworld Black Mirror The Prestige
children of men a Scanner Darkly
prisoners what do all these works have
in common they are all certainly
artfully crafted and rather unique but
more importantly they are cerebral
Radiohead's music tends to accompany
things that command us to think to get
more out of what's simply on the surface
the music basically is like mathematics
you know and you're trying to form
patterns for patterns that make you
understand what is around you and
patterns that help you get through the
next day Radiohead's music isn't just
background support it's not a needle
drop to get the audience excited
Radiohead's music is a tool a tool for
filmmakers to communicate ideas that
they simply cannot
[Music]